<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The miserable estate of the citie of Paris at this present With a true report of sundrie straunge visions, lately seene in the ayre vpon the coast of Britanie, both by sea and lande.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841587</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841587</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08919)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1325:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The miserable estate of the citie of Paris at this present With a true report of sundrie straunge visions, lately seene in the ayre vpon the coast of Britanie, both by sea and lande.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Wolfe] for Thomas Nelson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustrations on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marvelous, The --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Curiosities and wonders --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Paris (France) --  History --  Siege, 1590 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6181:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6181:1"/>
            <p>The miſerable eſtate of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Citie of Paris at this preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a true report of ſundrie ſtraunge viſions, latel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſeene in the ayre vpon the coaſt of Britanie, both by Sea and lande.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depictions of the aforementioned "sundrie straunge visions"</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for Thomas Nelſon. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6181:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6181:2"/>
            <head>The miſerable eſtate of the Cittie of Paris at this preſent, with a true report of ſundrie ſtraunge viſions, lately ſeene in <hi>the ayre vpon the Coaſt of Britaine both by Sea and lande.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He preſent and diſtreſſed eſtate of the Citie of Paris, as it is vnknowen to ſome, ſo it is well knowen vnto many thouſand perſons that daily féele the force and bitterneſſe therof. The ſame being moſt extreame and lamentable, I could doe no leſſe but lay it open to the view of the whole worlde that all the Cities in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome may take example by the ſame, and feare hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to attempt the like inhumaine, vnnaturall and moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly actions, which aboue all other that Citie hath ſundrie times committed, eſpecially in two points: firſt, in ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the bloud of many thouſande innocents, and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for reſiſting and rebelling from time to time againſt the authoritie of their Soueraigne and Chriſtian King, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they haue of long time péeuiſhly continued. For which their ſo inſolent crimes, doubtles almighty God doth iuſtly plague and puniſh them, the rather to make it knowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them and others, that he is a iuſt God, and will puniſh the bloud-thirſtie and wicked, as he hath promiſed, euen to the third and fourth generation.</p>
            <p>Such haue béene the crimes of thoſe proude and diſloyal Pariſeans, (who of late yeares liued in great proſperitie, and abounded in wealth) that in the life time of that bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſtie Butcher, and vnnaturall Murtherer of Chriſtians called the Duke of Guize, with the conſent of the Quéene mother and her aſſociates, ſuffered to be accompliſhed and performed within the ſaide Citie, a lamentable Maſſacre of many thouſand innocents in one night, and ſuch eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6181:3"/> as were of the flower and chiefe of the Nobilitie of France, the fact being yet ſo freſh in memorie, that the bloud of thoſe then ſlaughtered aſketh reuenge and craueth bloud againe vpon thoſe hard hearted helhoundes and their poſteritie, now maintayners of their vnholy League, that long time haue reſiſted the authoritie of the higher powers, and giuen their conſents to ſéeke the diſſolution and ruine of that kingdome, and the ſubuerſion of their King, his Crowne and dignitie Royall, as they haue doone from time to time. For which their ſo horrible actions, together with their gréeuous crimes and deteſtable pride, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, inceſt, gluttony, and ſuch like abhominable vices which they of long time vſed, it hath pleaſed God to ſende among them extreame famine (a ſharpe meſſenger of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge to puniſh them) whereby they are at this preſent in ſuch gréeuous diſtreſſe as it is lamentable to report. For the Citie is beſieged round about by the kinges power which is very ſtrong, and therby hath cut them off from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any victuals or other ſuccour whatſoeuer, their victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als within was ſpent long ſince, whereby they are in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eaſe for want of foode. They are enforced to eate Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Aſſes, Dogges, Cattes, Rattes, Mice, and other fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and vnaccuſtomed things for their ſuſtenance, yea that which is more odious in reſpect of their neceſſitie, it is ſayd that they are enforced to féede one vpon an other: and that through féebleneſſe and want of victuals they fall downe dead in the ſtréetes and in their houſes. A moſt lamentable and vnaccuſtomed thing to be done, yet conſtrayned ſo to doe by meanes of their want and gréeuous famine, which is now generally among them. This their neceſſitie may be compared to the want &amp; miſerable eſtate of the Iewes at the ſiedge of Ieruſalem, where death threatned the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all the inhabitants, thereby ſhewing them that for their wickedneſſe and wilfull ſtubbornneſſe their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is at hand.</p>
            <p>The Friers and Cleargie men who are the ring lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and principall gouernours there at this preſent time,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6181:3"/> perceiuing the great neceſſitie whereunto the Citizens would bée driuen, by meanes of their deteſtable perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, dealt pollitickely, ſending for the Citizens of Paris into ſeuerall Cloiſters &amp; religious Houſes within the ſame Cittie, and commaunded them to bring in all their warlike furniture which they had in their houſes, to the intent that they might ſée if they were ſeruiceable or not for warre, ſo when they had gotten al the ſame furniture of pikes hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards, muſkets, gunnes, dagges, ſwordes, and ſuch like, they detained their weapons and ſent euery man home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain deſtitute of any furniture, wherwith to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues if occaſion ſhould ſerue, whereby they haue weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the whole multitude of Citizens, and drawen the ſtrength of the Cittie into their owne direction and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, fearing leaſt that famine ſhoulde compell the generall multitude to rebell againſt them, and ſo conſtrayn the fatte fed Friers to yéelde to their daily outcries, which is to yéelde vppe the Cittie into the kinges handes, and to ſubmitte them ſelues to his mercy, which to doe they can not compell them for want of weapons. Some here may happely demaunde, why the Cleargie men and chiefe Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, will not yéelde it vppe as well as the reſt, rather then to taſte of famine and ſo to ſuffer ſo grieuous and cruell a torment, which is more bitter then death, but for aunſwer thereto let this ſuffice. The Leagers and Cleargy men of the Cittie, ſuſpecting long before that ſuch miſery would come to paſſe, did vitaile themſelues for a long time, ſo that thoſe eſpecially that are chiefe gouernours, Officers, Watchmen, and Guard to the Cittie, haue yet ſome ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient maintenance, neuertheles the ordinary Friers are not far differing from the generall ſtate of the lay men in that Citty, for they are almoſt ſtarued by reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their ſmall allowance, ſo that moſt of them looke like vnto wild men, whoſe countenance is leane and ſtearne, as willing to ſnatch at the quarter of a good dogge, as ſoone as any other, though it coſt twentie ſhillings, as at this preſent it is worth among them. This is the true eſtate of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6181:4"/> ſaid Citty and inhabitants therein, whoſe miſery is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſent of God, as a ſharpe ſcourge for their ſo great wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and diſobedience towards God and their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. Thus doth God ſtill harden the hearts of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, and maketh them wilfull, blinde, and fooliſhe in their owne fancie, that their puniſhment for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes might be the more ſharpe and grieuous. The Prince of Parma for certaintie hath entered France with tenne thouſand men of horſe and foote, but ſoone after hee paſſed the borders, intending to aide thoſe of the Legue, the Kings power gaue him a battaile and diſcomfited thrée thouſand of his men. They of the League are very ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull for that the towne of Moutriall in Pickardy is yeelded vp to the King, which is of certaine troth &amp; done verie lately. A generall Battaile is daily expected forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, betweene the Duke de Mayne and the Chriſtian King of Fraunce, for whome almighty God daily doth fight, and will doubtles ſpéedily deliuer his enemies into his handes, they are within foure leagues one of another on both ſides of a riuer. It is therefore very conuenient that all Chriſtians ſhould pray for the good ſucceſſe of the King, that it woulde pleaſe God to giue him victory ouer thoſe rebellious and traiterous perſons. At the comming of the Prince of Parma into the French countries, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported there was viſibly ſéene in the Aire to all his army, thrée raine bowes, and betwéene euery one of them the forme of a toade, and preſently the riuers ther about ſéemed nothing but bloud, and ſo continued for a ſhort ſpace, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his army was in great feare, and would willingly haue returned, but they were by their generall commaunded on paine of death to goe forwards. Sundry ſuch ſights haue lately béene ſéene vpon the coaſt of France, for one of her Maieſties ſhippes called the Vangard, being in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſeas, met with nine hulkes and flie boats of the lowe countries bound homeward from Spaine, where the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine examined them concerning ſundry matters, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things tolde him, that they being on the coaſte
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6181:4"/> of France, on the one and twentith of Iune laſt, in a place called Bell Ile, the Sea round about them was of the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of blood, for the full ſpace of halfe an houre, and nothing was to be ſéene but bloud, ſo farre as they could diſcerne, &amp; taking vp the water in their buckets, they could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it from bloud: this the Maiſter and other in the company did ſweare to be true. Moreouer in Iuly laſt paſt the ſaide ſhippe of her Maieſties called the Vangard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Sea, in an euening about ſetting time of the watch, all the men in the ſhippe at the riſing of the Moone, did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne in the ayre ouer the Moone the ſhape of a man, with a crowne on his head &amp; the king of Spaines armes plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſplaide, which continued viſibly to be ſéene for ſome ſmall ſpace, and ſoone after it was as a thing ouerthrowne and vaniſhed away, and ſéemed to them as though it were falling.</p>
            <p>All which viſions generall, by the coniecture of ſundrie of good iudgement, preſageth the ruine and confuſion of thoſe vnwholy Leaguers, vpholden by the Pope and the king of Spaine, and contrariwiſe the good ſucceſſe of the French King, whoſe ancient armes is the thrée toades. God for his mercie ſake daily defende and protect him, that he may vanquiſh all his enemies, which ſéeke and pretend his vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion, which God grant for his mercie ſake. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
